<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="PAP.xslt"?>
<pap>
	<author>Eric Wieser</author>
	<entry>
		<date>22/10/2010</date>
		<work>
			<description>Applied for L3 project</description>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<date>07/01/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Made a <a href="http://timeglider.com/app/viewer.php?uid=line_25e6ce18472eb55f41df63e03f6a1d14">Timeline</a>
			</description>
			<purpose>Planning</purpose>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>
				Found and read the <a href="http://rcj.robocup.org/rcj2011/soccer_2011.pdf">Rules</a>
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Knowing what I actually have to do
			</purpose>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>14/01/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Investigation into the physics of motors. Differential equations linking stall torque, free-running-RPM, mass, and robot configuration to velocity and displacement after a certain time.</description>
			<purpose>Help me choose an appropiately spec-ed motor for use in the robot</purpose>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>21/01/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Starting writing some code for the Holonomic drive system of the robot. Also, tried and failed to set up a Git repository.</description>
			<purpose>Starts to abstract away the robot control system</purpose>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>Various research on microcontrollers. Mbed is faster, and the IDE will drive me mad, but Netduino is slower, and will not. Also, I already have one of these</description>
			<purpose>Helps me decide on the microcontroller to use in the robot</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Stop stalling and buy a netduino</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>28/01/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Had a look at the rotacaster website, and sent an email to the owners</description>
			<purpose>Finding suitable wheels for the robot. Employee claims that custom mounts	will be tricky to attach, leaving two main options: Custom made wheels, using a CNC cutter, or buying LEGO compatible wheels, and making an axle connector out of polymorph</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Investigate the cost of custom wheels</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>29/01/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Read a book on kalman filters</description>
			<purpose>Could be used in control systems in the robot</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Do some more research into their application in inertial navigation systems - speak to the Robotics team mentor</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>01/02/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Experimentation with an accelerometer</description>
			<purpose>Trying to work out how feasible the calculation of position is through the double integration of accelerometer readings. Looks as though drift will be a real issue, so may not be appropriate.</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Consider other methods of localization, such as ultrasonic sensors and optical mouse encoders</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>04/02/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Looking up cables. It appears companies cannot design breakout boards in a way such that anything can connect to them</description>
			<purpose>Helps me decided how to connect together the electronics</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Look up custom made PCB solutions</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>04/02/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>More omniwheels</description>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<date>19/03/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Attended robocup UK final using Lego Mindstorms robots. Won every game 5:0 - software looking good</description>
			<purpose>Able to investigate ideas used by other teams, to help build a better robot. Qualified for Turkey, giving an extra target for my project. Compared the specs of other team's motors to the ones we plan to buy</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Get my act together and buy the parts</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<date>21/03/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Compiled preliminary shopping list of parts</description>
			<purpose>Can't build the robot without the parts</purpose>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>22/03/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Downloaded Eagle, and started designing a custom PCB, to check viability</description>
			<purpose>Will let me evaluate the cost of a custom made PCB. Apparently http://www.newburyelectronics.co.uk does a good deal</purpose>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>23/03/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Changed PCB design, in order to accommodate beefier motors</description>
			<purpose>Lets me build a faster robot</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Check current calculations in order to choose a suitable battery size</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>25/03/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>More PCB stuff</description>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<date>05/04/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Compiled a more comprehensive and final shopping list on Google documents (http://bit.ly/robocup-shopping-list), to allow collaboration with my teammate</description>
			<purpose>Eases the purchasing of parts, as all the information is in one place. Allows the total cost of the robot to be calculated, and the materials to be adjusted accordingly</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Keep looking into custom fabrication of parts</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry>
		<date>10/04/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Added weights to each component on the parts list</description>
			<purpose>The robot has a weight limit. We want to make sure that we do not go over this! By listing individual weights, it makes it possible to see which parts are weighing the robot down</purpose>
		</work>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software, electronics">
		<date>13/04/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Found out about yet another controller, the FEZ Panda II, which was released a few weeks ago. Much higher spec'd than the Netduino. Looks like procrastination paid off!</description>
			<purpose>Gives me YET MORE CHOICES.</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Narrow down the choices.</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>16/04/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Started seriously thinking about custom made wheels. Ordered a bunch of washers and oversized key rings off the internet. As you do.</description>
			<purpose>
				Solved the "ARGGHHH WHICH WHEELS SHALL I BUY ISSUE", along with the "HOW DO I ATTACH THE WHEELS TO THIS STUPID MOTOR" issue.<br />
				Inside of wheel can be custom made to fit keychain ring and motor hub perfectly.
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>CAD inside of wheel</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>17/04/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Teammate recieves split rings and washers. Measures them.</description>
			<purpose>Allows wheel to be accurately CADed</purpose>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>Inside of wheel CADed. Once for each of the three times he measured the parts wrongly</description>
			<purpose>Got more acquanted with the works of the CAD package I was using</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Make teammate use calipers to measure parts
		</todo>
		<todo>
			Get a quote for CAM of the wheels
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>19/04/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Got a quote for laser-cut aluminum from Microkerf.</description>
			<purpose>Gauge the price of custom manufacturing: ~£8 per wheel</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Combine other parts with the order to save set-up costs</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>24/04/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Made teammate use calipers. CAD wheel. Again.</description>
			<purpose>Final wheel design can be sent off for manufacturing</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Get another quote</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>04/05/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Parts arrive at teammates house.</description>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>
				Sign up for Dreamspark, download Visual Studio Professional. Install Visual Studio.<br />
				Install Visual Studio SP1.<br />
				Install .NET Micro Framework SDK.<br />
				Install the FEZ Panda II SDK.<br />
				Install the FEZ Panda II USB Drivers.<br />
				Reinstalled Git for the sake of it.
			</description>
			<purpose>Allows me to start writing code for the controller of the robot. Installing things is tedious.</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Learn C# so that I can start programming the chip</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>05/05/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Received FEZ Panda II from Teammate.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Software development can begin
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>
				Created a functional Git Repository <a href="https://github.com/eric-wieser/Robocup-Junior-Soccer-2011">on GitHub</a>.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Git Repositories keep track of all the changes being made to the code as itis being writtenn. That way, if a mistake is made and the software broken, the code can be reverted to a previous, working, revision. Additionally, all the code is backed up on the web</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Write some code to fill up the repository!</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>06/05/2011</date>
		<work commit="6514c65f1dab1bbdf697ae4e56c7bca511a12191">
			<description>
				Wrote some code to fill up the repository (Learnt C#)
				Made an LED flash.
				Made an LED flash twice as fast!
				Made an LED pulse slowly off and on using PWM
			</description>
			<purpose>Started to acquaint myself with the .NET MF API. Also, got rather bored of flashing an LED. Should've borrowed some more hardware!</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Find a component that isn't an LED, and experiment with it.</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics, mechanics, software">
		<date>07/05/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Met up with teammate, and played with all the other cool "toys" that had been delivered. Discussed batteries, and mutilated some 6AA battery cases to accommodate the Lego Mindstorms NXT rechargeable batteries we had.</description>
			<purpose>
				Getting hold of an IR sensor has allowed me to write a program to read its output, which will be required in the final robot.<br />

				Learnt that I should've checked dimensions after finding that the diodes were twice as big as I'd thought.
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Plug the IR sensor into an oscilloscope, and examine the trace as the ball is moved.</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics, mechanics">
		<date>12/05/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>Took the IR sensor into the electronics lab, and connected it up to a picoscope to examine it's behaviour</description>
			<purpose>
				Using a Picoscope allows me to monitor the behaviour of the sensor without having to worry about my software. I tested various methods of shielding: cardboard, tin foil, and black paper. None of them were very good.
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>Continue to experiment with shielding</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>15/05/2011</date>
		<work commit="7d59bb6faed79f0a1701">
			<description>
				Had another meeting with teammate.	Continued to experiment with shielding, to no gain.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Shielding is required in order to made the view of the IR sensors directional. Without shielding, the strength of the signal is independant of sensor orientation.
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<work commit="824122205fd9ab2f4d41">
			 <description>Tested some code to read from the US sensors</description>
		</work>
		<todo>Consult an expert to help with the shielding</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="mechanics">
		<date>29/05/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Assembled a bunch of omnidirectional wheels, now that all the parts have arrived. Surprisingly challenging. Checked that the washers were reasonably rigidly mounted
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Required for the robot. Nice to see the first mechanical part come to life.
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Start thinking about motor drivers
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>01/06/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Started prototyping a motor driver design, now that the wires have arrived.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Can't power the motors without a motor driver!
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Draw up and finalize the design, so that it can be assembled.
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>02/06/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Finalized motor driver design. Did some research on how you actually cut stripboard, then actually cut the stripboard.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Stripboard must be cut before any components can be soldered on. Design needed finalizing so teammate could arrange the parts on the chassis
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Drill holes in the stripboard, and neaten off the edges.
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>03/06/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Cut, drilled, and filed all 6 motor driver boards. Soldered components onto one. Left the others until design proven.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Motor drivers are required to use the motors. Custom drivers need to be built early, so that they can be replaced with commercial ones if all else fails
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Test the assembled motor driver board, and if it works, solder the other 5.
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>06/06/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Purchased a set of PCB spacers from Maplin.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Allow the electronics to be connected to the chassis
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>
				Designed a mockup of the power board
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Get a feel for how much space needs to be left on the chassis
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Continue to draft the power board design
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>07/06/2011</date>
		<work commit="1a2654f5b0e6769f678d">
			<description>
				Tested the software written a while ago with the brand new motor controller. Corrected a couple of bugs, and got a feel for the torque of the motor.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Justifies building the other motor controllers, since the design is now known to work.
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Finalize the power board design, so that too can be built and tested
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics">
		<date>08/06/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Assembled two further motor drivers, giving a full robot's worth
			</description>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Test the new controllers, to check that they also work. If so, attach them to a foamex chasis for testing purposes
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="software">
		<date>10/06/2011</date>
		<work commit="fefbf211834f2efc7828">
			<description>
				Wrote code for the yet-to-be shipped HMC6352 compass sensor
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Get ahead of the game, so when the chip arrives, it can be tested immediately
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Test the compass sensor, and fix the (almost certain) bugs in the code
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics software">
		<date>11/06/2011</date>
		<work commit="7077e06d503141c59ef8">
			<description>
				Tested the compass, found bugs, and fixed bugs. Working properly. Few obscure bits of the datasheet might be worth implementing, but it's not too important
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Saves me from having to use the LEGO HiTechnic compass sensor, which had a high chance of being blown up
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>
				Teammate built a mock chassis out of foamex display board, and we screwed the motors on. Connected them up to the battery, and gauged speed. Moved very quickly.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				Proves that the motors chosen are the right ones
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<work commit="f49f207c5a5780a7492e">
			<description>
				Attached motor drivers to the same setup used earlier, and found out that it didn't work. Two motor drivers got very hot, and weren't working. Spent quite some time trying to figure it out.
			</description>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Build another two motor drivers, and attempt to fix the broken ones
		</todo>
	</entry>
	<entry tags="electronics, software">
		<date>12/06/2011</date>
		<work>
			<description>
				Found out that there was a short under the PCB spacers, and fixed it. Scraped off the copper so it couldn't happen again
			</description>
			<purpose>
				No longer have to buy replacement L298 chips!
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<work commit="e8435a9d2c1a1c4d0361">
			<description>
				Rigged the robot up as before, and tried driving. Found that motors had very low torque at partial speed, and tweaked the PWM frequency until it increased.
			</description>
			<purpose>
				The robot needs fine control of speed. If this can't be achieved purely by PWM, some kind of closed-loop control might be required
			</purpose>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>
				Tested the holonomic drive code, and ironed out bugs
			</description>
		</work>
		<work>
			<description>
				Came up with a final design for the power board
			</description>
		</work>
		<todo>
			Assemble the power boards, and order the chassis
		</todo>
	</entry>
</pap>